Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 8 -- Letters to Franklin 1783 December-1786 Mss.B.F85inventory08
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 August 26; A.L.S. 4p.; Franklin, William Temple. Calais
    His safe arrival at Calais in spite of the dilapidated condition of his carriage; arrangements made with M. Dessein for its repair. His efforts to procure the English papers for Dr. Franklin at a cheaper rate. If enough travellers arrive to make up the price of boat, will cross the Channel that day. Desires news of him and M. [Louis Guillaume] Le Veillard, whose illness he deplores; has not much faith in magnetism but prefers it to such continual bleeding. Reminds him of the promised letter to Mrs. Clark.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 August 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Strahan, William. London
    Introducing Mr. [Thomas] Berdmore, the celebrated dentist, who goes to Paris on a pleasure jaunt. Visit he received lately from the Governor [Wm. Franklin]; glad there is nothing now to interrupt his correspondence with Franklin. Urges him to visit England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 August 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, William Temple. Calais
    Detained by contrary winds; hopes to get off before night.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 August 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Vicq d' Azyr, Félix
    Deputed by the Royal Society of Medicine to Send Franklin the tickets for their next public meeting; afraid Franklin's indisposition will prevent his being present; promises to send him the papers which will be distributed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 August 28; A.L.S. 4p.; Franklin, William Temple. Dover
    His arrival in Dover after a stormy passage; was sick the enire time; since sleeping and renewing his acquaintance with beefsteak and potatoes, feels better. Arrangements he has made in order that Dr. Franklin may receive the English papers at much less expense. Settlements in connection with the family picture of the Marquis de la Fayette and arrangements for sending it to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 August 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Harrison, Benjamin. Richmond, Va
    Recommending to Franklin's kind attention and civilities Mr. William Short, a man of considerable abilities, who goes to France to join his friend, Mr. [Thomas] Jefferson.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 August 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Shewell, Robert. Philadelphia
    Forwarding the Resolve of Congress respecting the seizure of the brig "L'Aimable Elizabeth" at St. John's, Newfoundland, by Nicholas Gill, Judge of the Court of Vice Admiralty at that place; letter from Mr. Charles Thomson, Secretary to Congress, asking Dr. Franklin to procure Mr. Shewell redress; direction given to Mr. John Warder of London in the prosecution of Mr. Gill; begs Dr. Franklin to write Mr. Warder on the subject, if it be deemed necessary.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 August 30; A.L.S. 3p.; Proth, J.F. Montréville near Verdun
    Report that the United States desires some French Catholic priests; offers his services.
    A. E. by Dr. Franklin. The Government of the United States in no way concerned with the appointment of priests; his recommendation therefore would not only be improper but of no use.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 August 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Besnard, ------. Courville
    Report that Franklin is in search of some one to locate iron mines in America and construct furnaces and iron-forges; offers his services.
    A. E. by Dr. Franklin. What he has heard is a mistake; everywhere in America are men skilled in locating and working iron mines; thanks him for his offer but cannot encourage him to leave his own country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1784. August ?]; A.L.S. 10p.; Masse, -----. Marseilles
    His former letter, enclosing certificate and asking for a place as domestic in an English household, has received no answer; begs for a reply.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1784. August ?]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Poissonnier, Pierre
    Reminding him of his promise to sign the Report [on Animal Magnetism] of the Commissioners of the Royal Society of Medicine; it will be presented by M. Albert.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 2; A.L.S. 5p.; Franklin, William Temple. London
    Account of his attack of fever and ague at Canterbury, his pushing on to London and his arrival at his father's; has been ill in bed ever since; his father and the landlady all attention. Has forwarded the various letters, together with the watch for Mr. [John Hyacinth de] Magellan and the packet of the Report [on Animal Magnetism] to Sir Joseph Banks. Lord Shelburne not in town at present; promises to carry out his instructions as concerns Mrs. Holt and to call on Mme. d'Hauteville.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Moutard, -----. Paris
    Presenting Dr. Franklin with twelve copies of the reports on [animal] magnetism.
    A. E. by Dr. Franklin, acknowledging and accepting the same.
  - to Benjamin Franklin with Franklin’s Draft of a Reply, 1784 September 3; A.L.S. 2p.; de la Valinière. Ingrande-sur-Loire
    His residence as a priest in Canada for twenty-six years; account of his subsequent misfortunes; desires to know whether the Catholic religion is tolerated in Vermont, whether he and those who accompany him would receive a grant of land along some river, and also the address of certain bishops who have established themselves not far from Canada; thinks many Canadians would embrace the chance of leaving their country.
    A. E. by Dr. Franklin. Catholic religion tolerated in all the States; lands not given gratis in any of them; knows nothing of the establishment of bishops mentioned; no provision made for transporting strangers to America; disapproves of enticing French subjects to quit France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Bridgen, Edward
    Introducing a particular friend, Mr. [Stratford] Canning.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 5; A.L. 2p.; Houdetot, Comtesse d'
    Has just received a letter from the Comte de Mirabeau from London where he has fled after a succession of lively quarrels with the Keeper of the Seals, following the loss of a law-suit against his wife; desires to attend to his business himself; afraid of being deceived by the printers and book-sellers there; begs Franklin for a letter to an honest book-seller, and one to Dr. [Richard] Price or anyone who would be useful to the Count in this emergency; hopes to wait on Franklin soon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Ox, Pierre. Paris
    Considers that he and his wife have seen nothing in Paris if they fail to see Dr. Franklin; their fellow-citizens of Bâle, Switzerland, will ask them this question first of all; begs for the honor of a few moments' audience.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 7; A.L.S. 6p.; Franklin, William Temple. London
    Has gotten the better of the fever and ague, but is still very weak; owes his recovery to Dr. [John] Jeffries, his landlady, his father and Peruvian bark; desires a longer congé, in order to accompany his father to the seashore for ten or twelve days; all of the nobility and gentry out of town; the habit of the English to try sea-bathing once a year, as they are all more or less troubled with scurvy. Visits he expects to pay; drank tea with the Paradise family; their gratitude to Dr. Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Chapel, Jacques. Valencicnnes
    Expects shortly to go to London on business; begs Franklin to give him a letter to the American Minister there with a request to point out the most reliable commercial houses.
    A. E. by Dr. Franklin. As yet there is no American Minister in London; has been too long absent himself to give the desired information.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 8; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Bailly, Jean Sylvain. Chaillot
    Sends the original document for perusal prior to his signing it the following day together with all the other Commissioners [to investigate animal magnetism]; although there is nothing secret in the work of the Committee, begs Franklin not to let it be seen, owing to certain articles, concerning which the Committee has not judged it proper to explain themselves; desires this letter burnt.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Lacoudrais, Nicolas Louis Guillaume. Honflcur
    Introducing himself as a merchant as well as Swedish Consul at Honfleur; no one at this port to look after the commercial interests of the United States; applies for the position of American Consul there.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Benincasa, L. Ancona
    Wrote to the Marquis de Castries, in his quality of Consul-General of France at Ancona, asking his advice as to the treatment of American vessels; the reply was to treat them as friends and allies of France, to write Dr. Franklin concerning the appointment of an American Consul; applies for this position for himself.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 11; L. in 3d P.; Adams, Mr. and Mrs. John. Paris
    Inviting Dr. Franklin and his grandson to dine with them, and begging the loan of one of his servants as both their men-servants are ill.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Grasse, Vicomte de. Toulon
    Asking Franklin's aid to procure him the decoration of Cincinnatus; gives an account of certain manoeuvres by which he protected the debarcation of General [John] Sullivan's troops; this would constitute a feeble claim to such an honor, were not Franklin to fortify the request by the greatness of his name.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 14; A.L.S. 3p.; du Calvet, Pierre. London
    Applies again for the money owing him by the United States; General [Sir Frederick] Haldimand has been recalled from Quebec; only needs money to prosecute his suit with success; has interested the Comtes de Vergennes and d'Adhémar in his case; begs Franklin to help him obtain his just dues.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Charrin, -----. Saint-Chamond
    Desires to know the surest and quickest means of being reimbursed for a contract of the Pennsylvania Loan Office, acquired in 1780 and due for payment in 1783; desires a word of recommendation to the Treasurer of Congress.
    A. E. by Franklin. American paper of no use in Europe; it ought to be returned to some person in America who may make the demand; no use sending any recommendation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Hüe, -----. Calais
    His aged mother left in the world without any other prop than himself; poor as he is, desires to bring her to live with him, unable to do this without the sum of 50 écus; applies to Franklin to help him accomplish this act of filial tenderness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Whatley, George. London
    Introducing Dr. [William] Rowley, one of the physicians in the London College; he goes to Paris to arrange for the publication of a work in Greek and Latin. Remarks on the choice of Franklin to look into the business of magnetism.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Barre, Mme. Baudoüin
    Will not despair of Dr. Franklin's ultimate assistance; implores him to take pity on her.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 24; A.L.S. 3p.; du Calvet, Pierre. London
    Concerning the debt due him by the United States; has just been informed by Mr. Lambert, banker at Paris, that he must write himself to Congress and forward the papers proving his claim; reproaches Franklin with not having kept his promise to write to Congress and thereby causing him a year's delay; explains the difficulties of settling this affair without Franklin's assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Canning, Stratford. Paris
    Promising to take care of the packet of letters received from Franklin; acknowledging those for America for Mr. Burrowes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Carmichael, William. Madrid
    Appointment of M. [Diego de] Gardoqui as Minister from Spain to the United States. Question of the "South Carolina" frigate and the indemnity claimed; his promise to write to the Comte de Galvez.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 140; Bigelow, IX, 61).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 25; A.L.S. 3p.; Glier, ------. Havre
    Writes on behalf of Thomas Dunlap who was arrested while sleeping in a stable where he spent the night for lack of better lodings; his wish to embark on a vessel going to America; has kept him in prison out of pity, as the poor wretch lacks for everything; applies to Franklin for further directions.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 26; A.L.S. 4p.; Franklin, William Temple. London
    Thanking him for the longer leave of absence; after all found that he could not spare the time to go to the seashore. Late dinners the rule in London; has only been to one play and got to that during the second act. Present at [Vinunzo] Lunardi's ascension; other balloon experiments. Will carry out Mr. [Thomas] Jefferson's commission. Desires half a dozen engravings from Duplessis's picture [of Dr. Franklin]. Dined twice at Cheam; Mrs. [Mary] Hewson has not yet said no; follows his instructions on that and every other head.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 29; A.L.S. 5p.; Newenham, Sir Edward. Belcamp
    Begs for news of him. Pleasure he experienced in entertaining Colonels Blagden and [James] Wadsworth. His plan to go to America in the spring with his eldest son, a friend, and two servants; expects to visit the capital of every state and part of the back settlements; desires information on various points as well as letters of introduction. Surprised at Mr. [John] Jay's return to America. Disgusted with affairs in Ireland; expects to retire from public life; agricultural and financial conditions. Description of a country-house he has just built; desires to protect it from lightning. The niche in the library awaits with impatience the bust of Franklin. His two sons returned from India; career of the younger altered.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 September 30; A.L.S. 4p.; Morris, Robert. Office of Finance Philadelphia
    Anticipates with pleasure his own resignation from office. Appreciation of Franklin's efforts to support the finances of America. Acknowledging his explanation of M. [Le Ray de] Chaumont's accounts. Bills for the salaries of Foreign Ministers. His admiration for Franklin's letters to the Comte de Vergennes relative to the attachments laid on the public goods. Disappointed at Franklin's postponed return to America.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 143; Bigelow, IX, 63).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1784. September ?]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Chabaud, -----
    Will leave on the 21st, for San Domingo, unless detained by orders from Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 October 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Fermin de Tastet and Co. London
    Concerning their escape from the financial difficulties brought upon them by the reigning Prince of Salm-Kyrbourg; they are now once more in a position to claim a continuance of Franklin's favors; cruel treatment of them by the Prince de Salm.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 October 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Fournier l’aîné, J. F. Paris
    Informed that Franklin is looking around for some one to teach his grandson [Benjamin Franklin Bache] the art of engraving; offers his services.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 October 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Pusignan, — de. Roanne
    Desires to know if there is any change of his obtaining the decoration of Cincinnatus; wounded at the siege of Yorktown; ignorance of the necessary formalities must excuse this application.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 October 5; A.L.S. 4p.; Franklin, William Temple. London
    Hopes for Mr. [Alexander] J[ohn] Alexander's success on his present attempt. His time taken up with invitations; regrets having to leave without seeing the "worthy Bishop" [of St. Asaph] and Lord Shelburne, who have sent him pressing invitations to visit them; question of the expense of travelling another consideration. Thinks he has executed all of his grandfather's commissions. His intimacy with the Comte de Mirabeau, who makes friends everywhere; urged by the Count to accompany him to Bath and to Lord Shelburne's.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 October 10; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Caraminico, Prince de. Paris
    Informing Franklin that he has had his first audience with Their Majesties and the Royal Family, in his quality of Ambassador Extraordinary of the King of Sicily.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 October 11; A.L.S. 3p.; Veillon de Boismartin, —. Les Sables-d'Olonne
    Account of the shipwreck of an American vessel in July, 1780, on the most dangerous rock off that coast; part he took in the rescue of the crew, passengers and mail; asks for the decoration of Cincinnatus.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 October 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Miles, William Augustus. Seraing
    At the request of his friend, Sir Edward Newenham, sends Franklin the enclosed printed extracts from the Irish papers; would be glad to hear of their safe arrival.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 October 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Pierres, Philippe Denis
    In accordance with Franklin's request, forwarded the letter to Mr. Hemery; his intention of waiting on Franklin and inviting him to dine.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 October 12; A.L.S. 4p.; Franklin, William Temple. London
    Arrival of the Abbê [Morellet] and Lord Fitzmaurice; possibility of his returning to Paris with the former. Mrs. [Mary] Hewson's acceptance of Franklin's proposal; they will be with him by the end of the month. His great liking for Mr. and Mrs. [John] Sargent with whom he has been staying; their strong attachment to Dr. Franklin; Mrs. Sargent's admiration for his Dialogue with Mme. la Goutte. Civility of Lord Stanhope and his son Lord Mahon. Dines that day with Mr. [John] Paradise to meet some members of the Royal Society.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 October 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Newenham, Sir Edward. Belcamp
    His reasons for desiring to be informed of the receipt of a copy of the Evening Post sent to Franklin; suspects it may be held back; the public much agitated by the late meeting; his own attitude. Reminds him of the wished-for letters of introduction.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 October 12; A.L.S. 2p.; d'Auzouer, Mme. Carroll. Paris
    Reminding Franklin of her visit to him in 1778. Concerning her relatives in America, one of whom was a Member of Congress; the last letter she received from him spoke of sending his son to France; fears he is dead; desires an hour with Dr. Franklin that she may ascertain something about her Maryland relations.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 October 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Ligne, Prince de. Brussels
    Recommending to Franklin's kindness M. de Vaux who desires to increase his moderate competence by work.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 October 13; A.L.S. 4p.; Franklin, William Temple. London
    Mrs. [Richard] Price's sad state of health; Mr. Price cannot introduce him to the Whig Club as it does not meet at present. Through the kindness of Dr. [Charles] Blagden and Mr. [William] Vaughan has attended two philosophical clubs; Franklin's health drank both times and many inquiries made concerning him. Has ordered a new kind of letter press, which is far superior to the old one in the office. The printing press ordered for Mr. [Thomas] Jefferson. Recommends that the rooms, for Mrs. [Mary] Hewson, her daughter and son, be made decent. Thinks Mrs. Clark really clever; she would not need much persuasion to be of the party to Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 October 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Viny, Thomas. Tenterden
    Congratulates America on her glorious emancipation and Franklin on his successful labors; good wishes for the future of that country and of Franklin's race. Much concerned that he has to endure so painful a complaint as the stone. Has given up the hope he once entertained of settling in America. Sorry to hear that any of the United States have blended civil and religious liberty.
  - to Benjamin Franklin with Franklin’s Draft of a Reply, 1784 October 15; A.L.S. 2 p.; Desfours l’aîne, —. Lyon
    Sent Franklin some months before a plan relative to the advancement of the United States, but has never received any reply; begs for the Commission of Captain in the American army, merely as supernumerary officer without pay.
    A. E. by Franklin. Has never received the plan mentioned but would be glad to see it. Has no authority to grant such commissions but will send his request to Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 October 15; A.L.S. 1 p.; Cannon, A. Theodore. The King's Bench
    Has served his ungrateful country sixteen years; has arrived at the honor of gaining the King's Bench as a recompense, and a Government discharge for the monies expended in its services; wishes to devote the rest of his life to the services of America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 October 16; A.L.S. 3p.; Marioge, -----. Câteau-Goutier
    Has read in the public papers of the desire in America for manufactories of all kinds; his knowledge of the manufacture of linens and the dyeing of various stuffs; offers his services.
    A. E. in French by Franklin. Thanks him for his offer but has no authority to encourage manufacturers to go to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 October 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Chevallié, Pierre François. Rochefort
    Enclosing copies of various documents which prove his claims on Congress, on the State of Virginia and on the Consul at Boston; begs Franklin's assistance in hastening the payment of the amount due.
    [List of papers enclosed.] 1. A memoir setting forth his claim to certain sums of money from the sale of the cargo of "Le Fier Rodrigue." [6 p.] 2. Copy of the arbitration decree rendered at Bordeaux between Messrs. de Beaumarchais and Chevallié. [4 p.] 3. Copy of the deed of sale for the cargo of "Le Fier Rodrigue." [2 p.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 October 20; A.L.S. 3p.; Du Bost, -----. Lyons
    His idea that the trembling of the earth lately felt at Lyons may have the same relation to the moon, as the high tides have; suggests ascertaining the period of the month when earthquakes have occurred, with a view to strengthening this hypothesis. Has another theory concerning the air as an instrument of transmission, which he wishes to send Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 October 21; A.L.S. 3p.; Price, Richard. Newington Green
    Acknowledging copy of the King of France's Edict establishing a sinking fund; his admiration for its spirit and wisdom; his failure so far to establish a like plan in England; expects to make another trial at the next session of Parliament. Experiments with balloons. Introducing Mr. Jonathan Jackson.
    Printed, in part, in Works (Sparks, X, 146).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 October 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Pierres, Philippe-Denis
    Sending him two editions of “Bon Homme Richard”; desires to be informed of Mr. W[illiam] T[emple] Franklin’s return; anxious to see the books he will bring from England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 October 22; A.L.S. 3p.; W[illiam] T[emple] Franklin. London
    Hopes all his letters have arrived safely. Mrs. [Mary] Hewson seems to have changed her mind; will see her again; date of departure unsettled; will wait till the next Thursday, as he is anxious to dine with Mr. [Benjamin] Vaughan to meet Dr. [Richard] Price and other friends of Dr. Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 October 22; A.L.S. 3p.; d’Inarre, —. Frankfort-on-the-Main
    Desires information as to the price of land and negroes and the incursions of savages in America; his wish to become a planter in South Carolina; his wife willing to accompany him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784, October 23; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Charretié, -----. Paris
    Sending the two parcels he brought from London; expects to wait upon Franklin on his return from Versailles.